A Guide to the Lewis Dabney Crenshaw Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #2681
Lewis Dabney Crenshaw Papers 1917-1936
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
2681
ca. 8,000 items
Mrs. Lewis Crenshaw
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Lewis Crenshaw of New York City, on May 24, 1947.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
This information was taken from Crenshaw's obituary notice which appeared in The University of Virginia Alumni News, February 1947.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection consists of ca. 8,000 items (12 Hollinger boxes, three linear feet) 1917-1936, and includes correspondence, financial papers, photographs and war service records pertaining to the operation of the European Bureau in Paris, France, the activities of University of Virginia alumni in World War I, the Jefferson [Founder's] Day Centennial Celebration in Paris, France, 1919,and the creation of the University of Virginia World War Veterans Association. The photographs and papers were gathered by Bureau Director Lewis Crenshaw(1884-1947) as part of the service of the UVA European Bureau and were later used to begin collecting information for a UVA War Record. All of the material is arranged chronologically except the photographs of the UVA alumni in uniform and their service records which are filed according to the last name of the alumnus.
The war service records contains the following information about alumni: name, place and date of enlistment, place and date of discharge, dates of foreign service, rank and organization at time of discharge, training camps attended, casualties, operations engaged in, honors and decorations, promotions, and non-military war service. This information is not necessarily complete for each alumnus. Both the service records and photographs are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the alumnus.
The correspondence files of this collection contain letters from family members concerning the status of soldiers, contributions to the upkeep of the UVA European Bureau, personal letters to Crenshaw, letters from UVA faculty and staff, copies of Crenshaw's correspondence, letters with addresses, rank, and war service records for some alumni, and letters from the soldiers themselves, often describing their experiences in Europe.
The UVA European Bureau opened an office on 8 Rue de Richelieu, Paris, to meet the needs of alumni serving overseas. Crenshaw maintained photographs and war service records for alumni, forwarded mail and cables, stored personal effects of the soldiers, handled routine financial matters, corresponded with family members, and often purchased and shipped articles for UVA men.
Crenshaw apparently kept these records hoping to eventually publish a War Record as a permanent record of the contributions of University of Virginia alumni to World War I. In 1930, members of the old Overseas Executive Committee, chaired by Ernest Schoen, began corresponding about the need for a War Record and a Reunion in France. The University of Virginia World War Veterans Association was formed in May of 1932, with Crenshaw as Director. The Association was authorized by the Board of Managers of the Alumni Association to compile, edit, and publish a complete record of activities of the alumni, faculty, and students of the University during the War, and to solicit the necessary funds for carrying out their plans.
The Association planned for the book to include the service record and a photograph of each alumnus, and to have special articles on the different Virginia units, the activities of the faculty and students, and to have a special section on the eighty alumni who died in the conflict. Perhaps due chiefly to the ravages of The Great Depression, the Association was unable to raise enough money to finance the book, although Crenshaw and Schoen were still discussing the war history as late as 1938. Crenshaw was never paid for his earlier work in compiling data for the book and often worked at his own expense.
Holsinger photographs present in this collection include: the UVA Ambulance Sections 16 & 17, U.S. Army Ambulance Service, with members identified; the UVA [Student Army Training Corp ?] unit in front of the Rotunda; a swearing-in-ceremony of the [Student Army Training Corp ?] in front of the Rotunda; the University Book Store(formerly known as Temperance Hall) and the Cheasapeake and Ohio Railway Ticket Office; Corner Businessmen and Henry Martin standing in front of the University Drug Store, Anderson's Bookstore, and the Southern Railway System Ticket Office; the University Book Store and Tea Room, later used as the Student Health Building; and Henry Martin, posing beside the University Bell.
For more information concerning UVA alumni in World War I, please consult
957-h
.
ORGANIZATION
All of the material is arranged chronologically except the photographs of the UVA alumni in uniform and their service records which are filed according to the last name of the alumnus.
Container List
- Biographical Information re Lewis Dabney Crenshaw, including photograph, n.d. (Box Box 1)
- Constitution and By-laws of the UVA World War Veterans Association, ca. 1932 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1917 Jan-1918 Jun; (6 folders) (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1918 Jul-Oct 1-18; (6 folders) (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1918 Oct 19-Dec; (5 folders) (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1919 Jan-Mar; (6 folders) (Box Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1919 Apr-Sept, 1920; (3 folders) (Box Box 5)
- Correspondence (Box Box 5)
- Correspondence of the UVA World War Veterans Association, 1932 Apr-1936 Jun; (3 folders) (Box Box 5)
- Correspondence re Jefferson Day Centennial Celebration, Paris, France, 1919 Mar 9-April 25 (Box Box 5)
- Correspondence with Ernest "King" Schoen, 1932-1935, 1937, 1938 (Box Box 5)
- Financial Papers: American Express Co. accounts, receipts, 1920 Jan-1925 Dec (Box Box 6)
- Financial Papers: Hotel Bills, 1917 Dec-1919 Jun (Box Box 6)
- Financial Papers: Miscellaneous, 1910, 1917-1933 (Box Box 6)
- Financial Papers: Miscellaneous, 1919-1933 (Box Box 6)
- Lists of UVA World War Veterans, Especially re Donations for an UVA War Veterans Directory, ca. 1918-1932 (Box Box 6)
- Miscellaneous, ca. 1918-1936 (Box Box 6)
- Papers re UVA Overseas Dinners, ca. 1918 (Box Box 7)
- Papers re Jefferson Day Centennial Celebration, Paris, France, 1919 Mar-Jul (Box Box 7)
- Photographs: Abbot - Butcher, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 7)
- Photographs: Cabell - Davis, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 7)
- Photographs: Derr - Harwood, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 7)
- Photographs: Hathaway - Julian, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 7)
- Photographs: Lancaster - Nash, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 7)
- Photographs: Ochs - Shepherd, R.G., ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 8)
- Photographs: Shepherd, W.R. - Warren, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 8)
- Photographs: Watkins - Wylie, unidentified, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 8)
- Photographs: Alsop - Fife, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 8)
- Photographs: Letcher - Williamson, unidentified, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 8)
- Photographs: Miscellaneous, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 8)
- Reports of the UVA European Bureau, 1917 Dec-Feb, June (Box Box 8)
- War Service Records: A-F, ca. 1919; (8 folders) (Box Box 9)
- War Service Records: G-O, ca. 1919; (6 folders) (Box Box 10)
- War Service Records: P-Z, ca. 1919; (6 folders) (Box Box 11)
- Lewis Dabney Crenshaw Calendar, 1919 (Box Box 12)
- Index to Lewis Dabney Crenshaw Calendar, 1919 (Box Box 12)
- Photograph of the UVA [Student Army Training Corp ?] unit in front of the Rotunda, ca. 1917 (Box Oversize Photograph Folder)
- Military Portraits, ca. 1918 (Box Oversize Photograph Folder)
- UVA Ambulance Sections 16 & 17, U.S. Army Ambulance Service, with members indentified, ca. 1917 (Box Oversize Photograph Folder)
- Fred Harper, ca. 1917 (Box Oversize Photograph Folder)